Register of the Richard A. Stratton papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Alice M. Stratton File, 1955-1994
  - Subject file, 1967-1974
    Contains material related to the Department of the Navy, the Stockholm Tribunal, and several POW/MIA advocacy groups, including some that Alice Stratton was involved in.
    - Big Brother, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 16: 4)
    - City resolutions to support POWs, 1970 (Box-folder 16: 5)
      Also see Oversize Material for "Resolution Honoring Our Returned Prisoners of War," Commonwealth of Massachusetts and Assembly Rules Committee California Legislature Resolution, relative to Missing in Action and Prisoner of War Tribute Day.
    - Committee of Liaison with Families of Servicemen Detained in North Vietnam, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 16: 6)
    - Department of the Navy, 1967-1973
      Contains correspondence, memoranda, newsletters, and printed matter Alice Stratton received relating to Richard Stratton's status as a POW and other information provided to families of American POWs/MIAs by the Department of the Navy.
      - Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 16: 7-8)
      - Memoranda, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 16: 9)
      - Newsletters, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 16: 10)
      - Printed matter, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 16: 11)
      - Miscellaneous, 1967 (Box-folder 16: 12)
        Contains correspondence of Charles A. Stratton, brother of Richard Stratton; undated typescript; handwritten notes; and a September 1969 news briefing of Lt. Robert Frishman and Douglas Hegdahl.
    - Friends of the POW/MIA League of Santa Clara County, 1967-1974
      - Board meeting files, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 17: 1)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 17: 2)
      - News clippings, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 17: 3-4)
      - Newsletters, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 17: 5)
      - Promotional material, undated (Box-folder 17: 6)
        Includes Christmas cards, pamphlets, and a poster, several featuring Stratton's photograph as a prisoner of war. Also contains a photograph of the 1972 Roll Call of the States event.
    - National League of Families of American POW/MIA in Southeast Asia, 1967-1974
      - Correspondence, 1969 June - July (Box-folder 17: 7)
      - Congressional records, 1970 August - November (Box-folder 17: 8)
      - Memoranda, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 17: 9)
      - Newsletters, 1969 March - 1971 December (Box-folder 17: 10)
      - Newsletters, 1972 January - 1973 August (Box-folder 17: 11)
      - Organization policy, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 17: 12)
      - Printed matter, 1969-1974 (Box-folder 17: 13)
      - Publicity campaign, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - United We Stand, 1970 March - August (Box-folder 18: 2)
    - Voices in Vital America (VIVA), 1971-1972
      - Annual report, 1972 (Box-folder 18: 3)
      - Bracelet records, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 18: 4)
      - Newsletter, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 18: 5)
    - Stockholm Tribunal, 1967 (Box-folder 18: 6)
- Photographs, 1960-2015
  Also see Oversize Material for additional photographs of Stratton as a POW in North Vietnam.
  - General, 1960-2015 (Box-folder 18: 7)
    Includes photographs of Alice Stratton, Richard Stratton's Navy portraits, the production of the "Honor Bound" sculpture, and photo negatives of Richard Stratton as a POW in North Vietnam.
  - Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Navy, Marine Corps Air Station Iwakuni album, 1986 February 6-7 (Box-folder 18: 8, Box 30)
    See Box 30 for the album's cover.
  - Hanoi Hilton, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 18: 9)
  - Oak Knoll Hospital, 1973 March (Box-folder 18: 10)
  - Quincy Public School, Homecoming Weekend held for Commander Richard Stratton album, 1973 November 10-13 (Box-folder 18: 11, Box 30)
    See Box 30 for the album's title page.
  - USS Powhatan, 1978 (Box-folder 18: 12)
- Digital Files, 2001-2015, undated (Box 26)
  Contains word processing documents and other digital files on optical discs. Arranged alphabetically by disc title.
  - "Alice Stratton DASN Resource Material and Background,", 2009-2013
  - "Alice Stratton Remarks, 1978-2013,", undated
  - "Disk I: R[eturned] POW - Background Resources; Dick - Pictures,", undated
    Includes photos, word processing files, and articles relating to American prisoners of war, torture, and communism.
  - "Disk II: R[eturned] POW - Background; Remarks & Friends,", 2001-2013
    Contains transcripts of speeches and addresses from 2001-2013.
  - "Hoover Institution Archives Inventory and Other Locations,", 2015
  - "North Vietnam, 1967-1973 ppt; videoclip USS Ticonderoga; VA192 NVN, 1966-1967,", undated
    Contains a PowerPoint presentation on North Vietnam, 1967-1973, and a video clip of the USS Ticonderoga, 1966-1967.
  - Photos of POW Day in Quincy, 2 discs, 2009 October 31
    Also see DVDs for a video of POW Day in Quincy.
  - "Stress of Separation Article and Supporting Documents, July 1978,", undated
  - Tales of Southeast Asia, 3 discs, 2009 February 9
    Contains a digital copy of Tales of Southeast Asia, photos, and Word processing files regarding a memorial in 2003. One of these discs is labeled as "POW SE Asia Misc."
- Sound Recordings, 1966-2012, undated
  Includes lectures, interviews, and speeches given by Richard and Alice Stratton. Arranged by media type and alphabetically by item title thereunder. Titles taken from item labels.
  - 1/4-inch sound tape reels, 1967-1978, undated (Box 26)
    - Interview of Richard Stratton by Todd McClaskey, 1978 May 1-3
    - "Lt. Robert Frishman 1969 Release," 2 reels, undated
    - "POW Documentary: Chief of Information Award,", 1975
    - "Stratton 'Confession,'" Voice of Vietnam, 2 reels, 1967 March 3
      A broadcast of the "confession" Stratton made while imprisoned in Vietnam, which criticized U.S. military forces. See also: compact sound cassettes.
  - Compact sound cassettes, 1966-2012, undated
    Arranged alphabetically by tape title. Titles were transcribed from the cassette tape labels when possible.
    - Untitled, 2 tapes, undated (Box 27)
    - Alcohol lecture, undated
    - Captain Jerry Coffee interview, undated
    - Captain Richard A. Stratton press conference, Chicago Press Club, 1977 June 9
    - Captain Stratton at Centereach High School, Long Island, New York, 1976 November 18
    - Captain Stratton interview, WOWT & KMTV, 1977 June 6
    - Captain Stratton interview by Jerry Bowen, CBS Morning News, 1977 July 11
    - Captain Stratton in Kansas City, 1977 July 14
      Side one contains an interview with the Kansas City Kansan and side two contains Stratton's appearance on WDAF-TV's Midday News.
    - Captain Stratton interview with Kansas City Star, 1977 July 15
    - Captain Stratton interview by Ken Sinclair, WKRS Radio, 1977 July 7
    - Captain Stratton's speech, Navy Leave/Joint Service Clubs, 1978 July 27
    - Cassette #1: "Captain Richard Stratton, May 10-11th, 1976, NBC TV"/"President Nixon White House Party, May 24th, 1973,", 1973, 1976
    - Cassette #3: "Bombing Reactions"/"POW Return: March 27th, 1973" (side one), "POW's Return/Captain Gene Wilber Interview 60 Minutes"/"President Nixon's Farewell Talk August 9, 1974" (side two), 1973-1974
    - Commander Fantry, 1974 October 5
    - Commander Stratton's homecoming at Oak Knoll Hospital, 1973 March
    - "Community Spotlight: Captain Richard Stratton," WJDA 1300 AM, 1976 June 14
    - Confession text (side 1) and DIA [Defense Intelligence Agency] taping of Stratton's "confession" (side 2), 1967, 1973
    - Costa Mesa speech, 1973 May 16
    - DASN [Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Navy] (Personnel & Families) interview, 1986
    - David Dellinger at University of Michigan meeting, undated
    - Explorer Scout Troop speech, 1974
    - Fleet Reserve Association Convention, 4 tapes, 1977 September 3
      Tape 1 contains the 4th Marine Air Wing Flag Pageant and welcome address by Jim and Dot Neal. Tape 2 includes speeches by Dan Kadrovack, Jos. V. D. Rosa, Percy Lemoine, Dr. Madden, Admiral Barrow, General White, Admiral Kamm, and Captain Richard Stratton. Tape 3 is the continuation of Captain Stratton's speech and presentations. Tape 4 contains a continuation of presentations and the conclusion of the opening ceremonies.
    - Graham Miller interview, 2012 March 15
    - Hanoi Japanese interview (side 1) and Hanoi "confession" (side 2), 1967
      Side two includes the Voice of Vietnam broadcast of Stratton's "confession," a statement while he was a POW in Vietnam, in which he criticized U.S. military forces in Vietnam.
    - Hoover Stratton collection contents, 1992
    - Interview report with Bernie Patterson by Charlie Stratton, undated
    - KMOX-TV (CBS) St. Louis, MO, 21 July 1977 and interview with Globe-Democrat, Al Schweitzer, 2 tapes, 1977 July 21-22
    - Letter to Alice and family after 1st line period, 1966 December
    - Mare Isle speech, Chief Petty Officers' Club, 2 tapes, 1973 August 25
    - "The Military Family," Captain & Mrs. Stratton, 1980 October 9
    - Molpus/Stratton, MacLeish commentary, Morning Edition, 1986 July 9
    - "Moral Decision Making: Captain Richard A. Stratton," Command & Staff College lecture, 1981 October 8
    - "POWS Are No Losers," speech, Lockheed Missiles and Space Company Management Association, 1974 July 17 (Box 28)
    - "Seeing Eye Dogs," Morning Edition, National Public Radio, undated
    - Shoot down and capture, 2 tapes, 1967 January 5-6
    - Speaker Richard Stratton, National Technical Institute for the Deaf, 3 tapes, 1978 January 19
    - Stratton talk at Naval Plant Representative Office, Bethpage, four years after release, 1977 March 10
    - Summary of selected summaries of Stratton's debriefs, 1973 March - April
    - Toastmasters Santa Clara speech, 1973 October
    - Town Topics, WANN 1190 AM, 1979 September 29
      Includes guests Captain Richard and Alice Stratton.
    - Vietnam: Hawk, Dove, Owl by Dolf Droge, undated
  - Compact sound discs, undated (Box 26)
    - "Hanoi Hilton: Piracy Today,", undated
      Part nine of the Empires of Gold & Jade lecture series by Dr. Jay Wolff.
- Motion Picture Films, 1973-1974 (Film shelf)
  16mm film. Contains film footage of Richard Stratton, including interviews and his biographical documentary.
  - 2251 Days, PBS KQED-TV, 1973
    Also see 2251 Days file in Military Career File and in Videorecordings/Videocassettes.
  - Arrival at Oak Knoll Hospital, 1973 March
    Mislabelled. Actually contains footage of a high school band.
  - Japanese interview with Lieutenant Commander Richard Stratton, undated
  - Sacramento TV interview, NBC-KCRA, 1974
- Videorecordings, 1973-2009, undated
  Contains video footage of Richard Stratton's television appearances, events related to Vietnam POWs, and other family footage. Arranged by format and alphabetically by item title thereunder. Titles taken from item labels.
  - 1/2-inch videoreels, 1973 (Box 31)
    - Contact, WBSN-TV, 1973 June 28
      Conversation with Commander Richard Stratton and Commander Patrick Carr, National Commander of the Veterans of Foreign Wars, moderated by John Corbett.
  - DVDs, 2006-2009, undated
    Mainly consists of recordings that were not mass produced. Titles below have been taken directly from the disc labels.
    - "3-5-73 POW Release," disc 2 of 4, 1 hour 26 minutes, undated (Box 33)
    - "1973 Press Conference, Oak Knoll Naval Hospital,", undated (Box 26)
    - "2006 Reunion: Banquet Presentation," (Box 26)
    - "Attack Squadron 192 (VA 192) and Airforce Carrier Attack 14 (CVA 14) 1966-1967 Clip," 7 minutes, undated (Box 26)
    - "Douglas B. Hegdahl, U.S. Army Special Forces SERE School," lecture, 2008 October 17 (Box 26)
    - "Hanoi Taxi Retirement," 5 discs, 2006 May 4 (Box 26)
      Also see Correspondence series for letter received regarding Vietnam POWs 2006 Reunion where the "Hanoi Taxi" was retired.
    - "NAM WFGD [Navy and Marine World Famous Golden Dragon] Video, Aircraft Carrier Attack 14/Carrier Air Wing 19/Attack Squadron 192, West Pacific, 1966-1967,", undated (Box 26)
    - "Navy Recruiting District New York 2nd Reunion: Stratton Keynote Speaker,", 2008 March 8 (Box 26)
    - "POW Day: Quincy,", 2009 October 31 (Box 26)
    - QIF [ Quincy in Focus] segments, circa 2006 (Box 26)
      Contains footage of Major Charles L. Bifolchi's burial at Arlington National Cemetery, the Quincy Vietnam Veterans Ceremony, and the Healing Wall's visit to Quincy.
    - "Quincy Vietnam Veterans Day Ceremony,", 2007 March 29 (Box 26)
    - "Richard A. 'Dick' Stratton, U.S. Army Special Forces SERE School," lecture, 2008 May 2 (Box 26)
    - Square dedication of Peter J. Gerry, Quincy Vietnam Veterans Memorial Service, 2 discs, 2009 (Box 33)
    - "USS Ranger, Aircraft Carrier Attack 61, September 1956 - July 1993,", undated (Box 26)
    - "The White House Salutes Our Prisoners of War, May 24, 1973,", undated (Box 33)
  - Videocassettes, 1973-2003, undated
    - U-matic, 1973-1988 (Box 31)
      - 2251 Days, 2 tapes, 60 minutes, 1973
      - "A Conversation with Commander Richard Stratton," KNTV - Community Affairs, 1975 May 1
      - "Ex-POW's Segment with Captain Stratton," ABC Good Morning America, 2 tapes, 1978 February 15
      - Nine in the Morning, WTOP-TV, 1976 June 16
      - "Razor Sharp" featuring the U.S. Navy's Flight Demo Team - The Blue Angels, with Roger Staubach, 1982
      - "Special Segment: POW School," NBC Evening News, 1986 May 14-15
      - U.S. Naval Academy honor concept lecture by Captain Richard Stratton, 1980 September 29
      - "Vietnam War POW Update: Richard Stratton," reported by Ron Miller, ABC Evening News, 1978 March 3
    - VHS, 1973-2003, undated
      - "Anchored," Navy News this Week, Navy Broadcasting Service, 1987 October 17 (Box 32)
      - "Anchored," Navy News this Week, Navy Broadcasting Service, 1988 December 3
      - At Home with Honor, documentary, 30 minutes, 1988 July 22
      - "Captain Richard Stratton at Reserve Officers Association Mid-Winter,", 1986 January 27
      - "Captain Richard Stratton," television interview at Hanscom Air Force Base, 2 tapes, undated
      - "CBS Reports: Vietnam,", undated
      - "Code of Conduct,", undated
      - "Family Support Center," 9:18 minutes, undated
      - "Guatemala 1988 F.B.B., Richard & Alice Stratton,"
      - The Hanoi Hilton, recording and commercial copies, 1987
      - "Marist College - Presenter Richard A. Stratton, Professor Ron Gauch, Business Ethics,", 1993 April 16
      - "Operation Homecoming: Joint ANA/MOAA Luncheon,", 2003 February 12
      - "Operation Homecoming: POW Panel Discussion, NAS Whidbey Island Base Theatre,", 2003 February 12 (Box 33)
      - P.O.W. Americans in Enemy Hands: World War II, Korea, and Vietnam, 93 minutes, 1986
      - "Priority: POW," Department of Veterans Affairs, 36 minutes, undated
      - "Shattered Lives,", 1989 June 13
      - Stratton family short clip, 1973 March
      - "Stress of Separation: Odyssey of 7 Years," 41 minutes, undated
      - Surviving: The Hanoi Experience, Defence Intelligence Agency, 52 minutes, undated
      - "USS Iowa," Good Morning America, 1988 April 22
      - "Vice Admiral James B. Stockdale, Naval War College,", 1986 May 27
- Memorabilia, 1972-2014 (Box 19)
  - POW bracelets, undated
    Includes two bracelets for Richard A. Stratton, one for Captain John W. Kennedy, and one for Lieutenant Commander Michael Estocin. Estocin was an operations officer for Attack Squadron 192 and friend of Stratton. Also see the Voices in Vital America in the Alice M. Stratton File for additional material on POW bracelets.
  - POW pins, undated
    Three pins supporting awareness for prisoners of war, including one welcoming American POWs home.
  - POW stickers, undated
  - Welcome home handkerchief, 1972
  - World Famous Golden Dragons insignia, 2014
- Oversize Material, 1967-1990
  - Disabled American Veterans stamp album, 1973 (Box 29)
  - Friends of POW-MIA League posters, undated
  - Life magazine, 1967 October - November
    Contains the article "U.S. Prisoners in North Vietnam" from the October 20, 1967 issue and the November 24, 1967 issue that contains a letter to the editor Alice Stratton wrote in response to that article.
  - Photographs, 1967 July
    Contains scenes of Richard Stratton as an American POW in Hanoi. Includes original description on the back of photographs regarding POW treatment.
  - Resolutions honoring POWs/MIAs, 1970, 1973
    Contains a resolution passed by the State of California's Assembly Rules Committee on April 29, 1970 and a resolution passed by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts on April 19, 1973.
  - VIVA scrapbook, 1972 (Box 30)
  - "Welcome Home!" scrapbook, 1973
  - National League of Families POW-MIA flag, 1990 (Oversize tube, Box 19)
    See Box 19 for information regarding the flag.
- Printed Matter, 1946-2010
  Contains news clippings, articles, books, periodicals, and pamphlets relating to the condition of American POWs in Vietnam and their eventual release.
  - News clippings, 1965-2010 (Box 20, Box-folder 21: 1-8)
  - Pamphlets, 1946-1980
    - American Ex-Prisoners of War: A Modern Day Tragedy, 1980 June 17 (Box-folder 21: 9)
    - "Ending the War and Restoring Peace in Vietnam," U.S. Treaties, Vol. 24, 1973 (Box-folder 21: 10)
    - Faith Behind Barbed Wire by Patrick O'Connor, 1954 (Box-folder 21: 11)
    - Father Kapaun: The Ordeal of Father Kapaun by Lt. Ray Dowe Jr. as told to Harold H. Martin, 1954 January 16 (Box-folder 21: 12)
    - A Few Notes on the Manipulation of Human Behavior, Fleet Aviation Specialized Operational Training Group, Pacific Fleet, undated (Box-folder 21: 13)
    - Geneva Convention Relative to the Treatment of Prisoners of War, Student Handout, Survival, Resistance and Escape School, 1949 August 12 (Box-folder 21: 14)
    - Greater Love Hath No Man: Eight Years of Commentary on American Prisoners of War and Americans Missing in Action, 1973 (Box-folder 22: 1)
    - Hearing on Problems of Prisoners of War and Their Families Before the Committee on Armed Services, House of Representatives, 1970 March 6 (Box-folder 22: 2)
    - How You Can Help Our Prisoners of War, Forgotten Americans Committee, 1970 September (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - Lest We Forget, POW Concern, 1970 (Box-folder 22: 4)
    - North Vietnam Against U.S. Air Force, 1967 (Box-folder 22: 5)
    - Prisoners of War by Commander Philip R. Holt, undated (Box-folder 22: 6)
    - PW [Prisoner of War]: Your Rights and Obligations under the Geneva Convention, 1969 September 1 (Box-folder 22: 7)
    - Synopsis of News Events, January 1965 - June 1971, Fleet Intelligence Center, Pacific (Box-folder 22: 8)
    - U.S. Army Aircraft, 1908-1946 (Box-folder 22: 9)
    - U.S. Pacific Fleet, undated (Box-folder 22: 10)
    - Vietnam Information Notes Office of Media Services, Bureau of Public Affairs, Department of State, 1967 August (Box-folder 22: 11)
    - We Must Free the Prisoners by R. D. Patrick Mahoney, 1970 December 23 (Box-folder 22: 12)
  - Periodicals, 1967-1990
    - Air Force and Space Digest, 1969 October (Box-folder 22: 13)
    - All Hands, 1982 September (Box-folder 22: 14)
    - American Heritage, 1978 August-September (Box-folder 22: 15)
    - Aviation Week & Space Technology, 1973 April 23 (Box-folder 22: 16)
    - Brown Alumni Monthly, 1990 September (Box-folder 22: 17)
    - In Brief for the POW: A Catch-up on News from Missing Years, 1972 (Box-folder 22: 18)
    - Commanders Digest, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 22: 19)
      Contains issues from 1967 October 21, 1971 January 16, and 1973 December 6.
    - DAV [Disabled American Veterans], 1977 January (Box-folder 22: 20)
    - Direction, the Navy Public Affairs Monthly, 1973 July (Box-folder 22: 21)
    - Georgetown Today, 1977 January (Box-folder 22: 22)
    - Liberation, 1967 May - June (Box-folder 22: 23)
    - Legion, 1968 July (Box-folder 22: 24)
    - The Mariner, 1980 September (Box-folder 22: 25)
    - Marine Corps Gazette, 1982 April (Box-folder 22: 26)
    - The Military Chaplain, 1979 July - August (Box-folder 22: 27)
    - Newsweek, 1976 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - The Officer, Reserve Officers Association of the United States, 1986 March (Box-folder 23: 2)
    - People Weekly, 1978 June (Box-folder 23: 3)
    - Proceedings, U.S. Naval Institute, 1985 September, 1986 April (Box-folder 23: 4)
    - Time magazine, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 23: 5)
      Contains issues from 1972 November 6, 1973 June 18, and 1974 July 29.
    - Veterans of Foreign Wars Magazine, 1976 October (Box-folder 23: 6)
  - Books, 1964-1987
    - A-4 Skyhawk in Action by Lou Drendel, 1973 (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - A Living Tradition: United States Navy Memorial, by John W. Alexander, 1987 (Box-folder 23: 8)
    - Naval Air Training and Operating Procedures Standardization Flight Manual: Navy Model A-4E Aircraft, 1964 February 1 (Box-folder 23: 9)
      Flight handbook for the type of aircraft Richard Stratton was shot down in, in January 1967, 15km south of Than Hoa, North Vietnam.
    - On Strategy: The Vietnam War in Context, 1981 April (Box-folder 23: 10)
    - Prisoner at War: The Survival of Commander Richard A. Stratton by Scott Blakey, 1978 (Box-folder 24: 1)
    - The United States Air Force in Southeast Asia, 1961-1973 by Carl Berger, 1977 (Box-folder 24: 2)
    - USS Ranger, CVA-61: Western Pacific Cruise 1960, undated (Box-folder 24: 3)
    - USS Ranger: Western Pacific 1961-1962, undated (Box 25)
    - USS Ticonderoga, CVA-14, undated (Box 25)
    - What You Should Know About Vietnam: An Associated Press Close-to-the-News Book, 1967 (Box 25)